"How Not to Die Documentary"
There's an emerging
consensus that what's good
for our hearts is also good for our heads
because clogging of
arteries inside the brain
with atherosclerotic plaque is thought
to play a role in the
development of Alzheimer's.
This is what our cerebral
arteries should look like.
Open, clean, allowing blood
to flow throughout our brain.
This is what atherosclerosis
in our head looks like.
Clogged with cholesterol,
closing off arteries,
clamping down on blood flow.
What kind of brain arteries
do you want in your head?
(intense music)
As dementia is one of our
greatest public health problems
and the most feared
condition of later life,
there's kind of misconception
that we have no control over
whether or not we develop dementia.
But the good news is that
although Alzheimer's may be incurable,
at least it is preventable.
Too much cholesterol in our blood
is unanimously recognized
to be a risk factor
for the development of
Alzheimer's disease.
(intense music)
- According to the Global
Burden of Disease study,
our largest study of risk
factors is in human history.
The number one cause of
death in the United States
is the American diet.
Number one killer of men and women,
bumping tobacco smoking to number two.
Tobacco now only kills about
500,000 Americans every year,
whereas our diet kills many more.
So it's the number one cause of death.
Then obviously it's the number one thing
your doctor talks to you about, right?
Obviously it's the number one thing.
I mean, you know, but no.
- It's so dismal to have patients come in
with these reversible diseases
and just tell the patient,
"Oh, well I just have to
increase your statin dose
and come back in a month.
At that point you're an
enabler of their disease.
- Why do we have the
medical system we have,
which I consider to be flawed?
A lot of good people working
in that community, obviously,
but they're corrupted by a paradigm
that's been hanging over our
heads for more than a century.
- We're trained to use drugs in surgery.
We're reimbursed to use drugs in surgery,
so we use drugs in surgery.
Abraham Maslow once said,
if the only tool you have is a hammer,
you tend to see everything as a nail.
And I think there's a
lot of truth to that.
- If we could get people
to eat to save their heart,
it would markedly diminish the likelihood
of acquiring these common
Western cancers of breast,
prostate, colon, and pancreatic.
- So many times I have patients who come
and tell me, their doctor said,
"Your inflammatory bowel disease
has nothing to do with nutrition.
Don't worry about it.
You just get medications
and you're gonna be fine."
You couldn't be farther from
the truth if you think that.
(intense music)
- This is an investment
in your future self,
that future self may be six months.
That future self may be a
year, it may be 10 years.
There is so much value in that
because we all can say,
"I don't mind dying."
It's not about dying.
It's about are you
shortening that health span
and now you're sitting there
for five years, 10 years,
12 years, a shell of yourself.
You can neither live nor die.
Who wants to live that life?
- I am a surgeon, a bariatric surgeon,
so I operate on obesity
and I also am boarded in
medical management of obesity.
So I do both surgery and medical
management for weight loss.
Funny enough, as a doctor,
you would think I would know better,
but I had no training in
nutrition as a doctor.
Even in my training in
weight loss surgery,
I had no training in diet as a doctor.
In fact, as a weight loss surgeon,
we kind of felt like
diets just don't work.
- Allow me to begin
on a personal note.
This is a picture of me
taken around the time
that my grandmother was diagnosed
with end stage heart disease
and sent home to die.
(intense music)
The killer I'm talking about
is coronary heart disease.
Plaque accumulates inside
the coronary arteries,
the blood vessels that crown the heart,
and it's affecting nearly everyone
raised on the standard American diet.
(waves whooshing)
(heart beating)
At that time, the medical
profession didn't even think
it was possible to reverse heart disease.
Drugs were given to try
to slow the progression
and surgery was performed to
circumvent clogged arteries
to try to relieve symptoms.
But the disease was expected to get worse
and worse until you die.
(upbeat music)
She already had so many bypass surgeries,
basically run outta
plumbing at some point,
confined in a wheelchair,
crushing chest pain.
There was nothing more they could do.
Her life was over at age 65.
(upbeat music)
(waves whooshing)
(intense music)
I think what sparks many kids
to wanna become doctors when they grow up
is watching a beloved relative
become ill or even die.
But for me, who's watching
my grandma get better.
Eventually I heard about
this guy, Nathan Pritikin,
one of our early lifestyle
medicine pioneers,
and what happened next
is actually detailed
in Pritikin's biography.
My grandma was one of
the death's door people.
Francis Greger, my grandmother
arrived in wheelchair.
Mrs. Greger had heart
disease, and claudication.
Her condition so bad
she can no longer walk.
- Heart disease is the
nation's number one killer.
It accounts for half of all the deaths
in the United States.
This year, more than 1 million
Americans will die from it.
One reason almost all doctors
agree is the way we eat.
Nathan Pritikin is not a
doctor, not even a nutritionist.
Pritikin discovered he had heart
disease, which he reversed,
he says, by changing his diet.
Would you say flatly
that you can reverse
serious heart disease?
- I would say that we can take
the most serious heart disease
and return them in many
cases to normal function.
- We found we could reverse heart disease
in just three weeks.
When you make really healthy changes,
most people feel so much
better so quickly, it reframes
the reason for making these
changes from fear of dying,
which is not sustainable,
to joy and pleasure
and love and feeling good, which are.
- The normal American diet,
is so toxic to the body
that practically no human can stand up
against that kind of assault.
In fact, almost anyone over
20 years old in this country,
I can almost guarantee
you by autopsy studies
has some closed arteries already.
- 20
- 20, right.
- Atherosclerosis, harden of the arteries,
is a disease that begins in childhood.
By age 10, nearly all kids
raised on the standard
American diet already
have fatty streak building
up inside of their arteries
the first stage of the disease.
These streaks then turn
into plaques in our 20s,
get worse in our 30s,
and then can start killing us off.
In our heart causes a heart attack,
in our brain, the same disease
process causes a stroke.
So if there is anyone here this morning,
older than age 10,
(audience laughing)
then the question is not
whether or not to eat healthy
to prevent heart disease.
It's whether you wanna
reverse the heart disease
you likely already have,
whether you know it or not.
But is that even possible?
You know, when researchers
took people with heart disease,
put them on the kind of plant-based diet,
followed by populations
that do not get epidemic heart disease,
their hope was maybe we
could slow the disease down
a little bit, maybe even stop it.
Instead, something miraculous happened.
As soon as people stopped
eating an artery clogging diet,
their bodies were able to start
dissolving that plaque away,
opening up art without
drugs, without surgery,
suggesting their bodies wanted
to be healthy all along,
but we're just never given the chance.
This remarkable improvement
in the blood flow
to the heart muscle itself
was after just three weeks
of plant-based nutrition.
(intense music)
Imagine if terrorists created a bio agent
that spread mercilessly claiming the lives
of nearly 400,000 Americans every year.
We'd marshaled the army,
march in our finest
medical minds into the room
to figure out a cure for
this bio-terror plague.
In short, we'd stop at nothing
until the terrorists were stopped.
This particular biological
weapon may not be a germ
released by terrorists,
but it kills more Americans annually
than have all our past wars combined.
It can be stopped, not in a laboratory,
but right in our grocery stores,
kitchens, and dining rooms.
As far as weapons go, we don't
need vaccines or antibiotics.
(water whooshing)
A simple fork will do.
(intense music)
Nathan Pritikin gaining a reputation
for reversing terminal heart disease,
opened a new center in California,
and my grandmother in desperation
somehow made the cross country trek
to become one of his first patients.
This was a live-in program
where everyone was placed
on a plant-based diet
and then started on a
graded exercised regimen.
Within three weeks though,
not only was she out of her wheelchair,
she was walking 10 miles a day.
Here's a picture of my grandma
15 years after doctors
had abandoned her to die.
Though she was giving her
medical death senses at age 65,
thanks to a healthy diet,
was able to enjoy another
31 years on this planet
till age 96 to continue to
enjoy our six grandkids,
including me.
That's why I went into medicine.
(intense music)
(audience cheering)
- I remember her going out to Pritikin,
she came back and she was overly...
She'd look at the bread
that I had and said,
"What? This has oil in
it, or it has souls in it.
Or it has this in it,
and you're killing everybody."
You see, we lived near her
when we were living in
Florida temporarily.
Yeah, she lived to 96.
- 96.
(intense music)
A plant-based nutrition appears
to be the principle
component, alone accounting
for about half the difference in lifespan.
No wonder since the number
one risk factor for death
in the United States
is the American diet.
Now, if you can read here,
you know, unsafe sex, bad.
Sedentary lifestyle, bad.
Alcohol and drugs,
particularly tobacco, bad,
but cigarettes now only kill
about a half million Americans every year,
whereas our diet kills many more.
We are what we eat, which is good news
because it means we have the power.
We're talking about life and death here.
You go online and you hear,
you know, people spouting,
you know, nutritional
nonsense with some, you know,
corrupting commercial
influencers or something.
And it's not like someone
is lying to you to get you
to buy their brand of toothpaste.
But when someone says, you know,
"Here, eat this bacon and butter diet,"
we're talking about people
that could die over this.
These are life and death decisions.
Remember diet number one cause.
If there was any decision
to be made in life based on evidence,
it should be what to feed
ourselves and our family.
It's the most important decision
as to how long we and our loved ones live.
- It makes me want to apologize
to patients everywhere
for the practitioners of my profession,
who, I have to be charitable here,
but we're not taught
anything about nutrition.
Most doctors don't respect nutrition,
even though they're seeing
nutrition based diseases all day
in their clinic, and they're eating
the same foods themselves.
They're eating the burgers and
the pizzas and the lobsters
and the steaks,
they're not gonna tell
their patients don't eat it.
- When you hear all the
diets that are out there,
there's only one that I'm aware of
that has ever taken patients
who are seriously ill
with heart disease and
be able to get a halting
of the disease and
reversal of the disease.
And that's whole food,
plant-based nutrition.
It doesn't happen with paleo,
it doesn't happen with keto,
doesn't happen with Atkins,
doesn't happen with Agatston
or Barry Sears or you know,
these are all caring physicians,
but when the research is
done, it's whole food,
plant-based nutrition,
it will halt and reverse heart disease.
- In this country, when
doctors are trained,
there's not a medical
school in the United States
that teaches nutrition.
- We published a paper
recently where we surveyed
how much nutrition training
does the average doctor get
in four years of medical school?
And it turns out it's
about four hours a year.
You know, and even then
it's really about, you know,
vitamin C and scurvy and vitamin B
and beri-beri, things like that.
And then we looked at the average amount
of training in nutrition the
average cardiologist gets
in four years of fellowship
training, and it's a zero.
- Time and again, is so
apparent they had very little
information whatsoever about nutrition,
either in medical school or in
their postgraduate training.
- We have in this country, for example,
about 130 different medical specialties.
And those medical specialties,
they document their
experience with a patient.
And so it turns out that
all 130 medical specialties,
there's not one called nutrition.
- We're talking about
life and death situations.
We need to stop eating animal products
with high saturated fat, high
sugar, refined carbohydrates.
If we do all that, which
would be a whole food,
plant-based diet, and
we're doing the exercise,
we're paying attention to
our weight, blood pressure,
cholesterol, no one smoking.
We can actually do this. It's not hard.
- So does the American Heart Association
recommend a no meat?
No, they recommend this low meat diet,
the so-called DASH diet.
So wait a second, when this
DASH diet was being created,
I mean, were they just not aware
of this landmark research
done by Harvard's Frank Sacks?
No, they were aware.
The chair of the design
committee that came up
with the DASH diet was Frank Sacks.
See the Dash diet was created to try
to get the benefits of eating
a more plant-based diet,
yet contain enough animal
products to make it palatable
to the general population.
They didn't think the public
could handle the truth.
Now, I mean, in their
defense, you can kind of see
what they were thinking, right?
Just like drugs never work
unless you actually take them.
Diets never work at all
unless you actually eat them.
So they're like, look how many people
are gonna eat strictly plant-based, right?
If we soft pedal the message,
come up with some kind
of compromised diet,
well then on a population scale,
we might do more good.
Okay, tell that
to the thousand American families a day
that lose a loved one
to high blood pressure.
Maybe it's time to start
telling the American public
the truth.
(audience clapping)
Which is that in the
United States of America,
most deaths are preventable
and related to nutrition.
The number one cause of
death in these United States
is the American diet.
- When Western Medicine talks
about disease prevention,
they're really talking
about early diagnosis.
They're not talking
about not getting sick,
they're talking about, let's catch it
when you first get sick.
So there's colonoscopy
and there's mammogram,
and you know, lab tests like PSA
and things like that for prostate cancer.
So we're never telling someone,
"Hey, this is how you eat
to not get colon cancer,"
or, "This is how you eat to
not get prostate cancer."
Because really in the mind of a doctor,
they almost don't think of food
having anything to do with this.
It's almost like disease is just bad luck.
Like I really literally
thought that our bodies,
it was almost like, you
know, how you get a car,
you call it a lemon 'cause it's
a bad car, it's gonna break.
That's what I saw the human body as.
I mean, it's gonna break
down and I'm a fix it guy
and I'm gonna fix it up with my tools
and you stay outta the way.
Let me do my job and you'll be fine.
I switched onto a more plant-based diet.
I thank God there were
a few doctors out there
that had written some papers
and I started doing research
and the more research I did, I was like,
oh my God, it is the food that we eat
and it's the exact
opposite of what I'm eating
and what I'm telling patients.
And then of course I start
looking around my patients.
Everybody's got the same diseases
and they're not separate diseases.
We think of them separately.
We think there's obesity
and there's heart disease
and there's cancer and there's diabetes.
They're all one disease process.
I mean, they're all part
of an inflammatory process.
- How can there be this
disconnect between the science
and the practice of mainstream medicine?
Well, let's do a little
thought experiment.
Imagine yourself a
smoker back in the 1950s.
The average per capita
cigarette consumption,
4,000 cigarettes a year.
(intense music)
The media was telling people to smoke.
Famous athletes agreed,
even Santa Claus wanted you to smoke.
(audience laughing)
I mean, look, you wanna keep fit
and stay trimmed so you make sure to smoke
and eat lots of hot dogs to stay trim
and you eat lots of sugar to stay slim
and trim a lot better
than that apple there.
I mean, shees, right?
Hey, but "Apples do connote
goodness and freshness,"
reads one internal tobacco industry memo,
which brings up "many possibilities
for a youth-oriented."
They wanna make apple flavored cigarettes
for kids, shameless.
"For digestion sake, you should smoke."
I mean, "No curative power
is claimed by Philip Morris,"
but hey, better be safe
than sorry and smoke.
"Blow in her face and
she'll follow you anywhere."
(audience laughing)
After all, no woman ever says, no.
They're "So round, so
firm, so fully packed."
(audience laughing)
After all John Wayne smoked them
until he got lung cancer and died.
(intense music)
You know, back then even the
paleo folks were smoking.
And so were the doctors.
Now, this is not to say
there wasn't controversy
within the medical profession.
I'm sure you know, some
doctors smoke Camels,
but others preferred Lucky.
So there was a little disagreement there.
The leader of the US Senate agreed,
who wouldn't want to give
their throat a vacation?
Not a single case of throat irritation.
How could there be when
"Cigarettes are just as pure
as the water you drink?"
But anyway, if your throat
does get a little irritated,
don't worry because your
doctor can always write you
a prescription for cigarettes.
This is in
the "Journal of the American
Medical Association."
So when the AMA is on record saying
that smoking on balance
may be good for you,
where could you turn back then
if you just wanted the science?
I mean, what's the new
data advanced by science?
Well, she was, "Too tired for fun
and then she smoked a camel."
(audience laughing)
Babe Ruth spoke of proof
positive medical science
that is when he still could speak
before he died of throat cancer.
If by some miracle back then
there was some kinda
smokingfacts.org website
that could have delivered
the science directly,
bypassing commercially
corruptible institutional filters,
you would've become aware
of studies like this.
There's an Adventist
study outta California
published in 1958 showing that non-smokers
had at least 90% less
lung cancer than smokers.
But this wasn't the first.
When famed surgeon Michael DeBakey
was asked why his studies back in the '30s
linking lung cancer and smoking
were simply ignored off
the face of the planet,
he had to remind people
what it was like back then.
We were a smoking society.
It was in the movies on airplanes,
medical meetings were
one heavy haze of smoke.
Smoking was, in a word, normal.
(intense music)
So back to our thought experiment.
Imagine you're a smoker
in the '50s in the know.
What do you do?
I mean, with access to the science,
you realize the best
available balance of evidence
suggest your smoking habits,
ah, not so good for you.
So do you change or do you wait?
If you wait until your doctor tells you
between puffs to quit,
you'd have cancer by then.
If you wait until the powers that be
officially recognized it,
like the Surgeon General did
in the subsequent decade,
you could be dead by then.
It took more than 25 years,
it took more than 7,000 studies
and the deaths of countless smokers
before the first Surgeon General
report against smoking came out.
You'd think maybe after
the first 6,000 studies
could give people little
heads up or something.
Powerful industry.
Maybe we should have stopped smoking
after the 700th study like this came out.
But as a smoker in the
'50s, on one hand you had
all of society, the government,
the medical profession
itself telling you to smoke.
And on the other hand, all
you had was the science.
If you're even aware of studies like this.
Let's fast forward 55 years.
You know, there's a new
Adventist study outta California
warning Americans about something else
they may be putting in their mouths.
Of course, it's not just one study,
put all the studies together
and deaths from all causes put together,
including many of our dreaded diseases,
stroke, cancer, significantly lower
among those eating more plant-based diets.
So instead of someone going along
with America's smoking habits in the '50s,
imagine you or someone you know
going along with America's
eating habits today,
what do you do?
I mean, with access to the science,
you realize the best available
balance of evidence is yes,
you're eating habitant
not so good for you.
So do you change or do you wait?
I mean, if you wait until
your doctor tells you
between bites to quit,
it could be too late.
In fact, even after the Surgeon
General's report came out,
the American Medical Association
officially went on record
refusing to endorse it, why?
Could it have been
because they were just
handed a $10 million check
from the tobacco industry, maybe.
Okay, so we can see why
the AMA was sucking up
to the tobacco industry,
but why weren't more
individual doctors speaking up?
There were a few, ahead of their time,
speaking up against
industries killing millions.
But why not more?
Maybe it's because
the majority of physicians
themselves smoked cigarettes.
Just like the majority of physicians today
continue to eat foods
that are contributing
to our epidemics of dietary disease.
What was the AMAs rallying cry back then?
Everything in moderation.
Extensive scientific studies,
proven smoking in moderation.
Oh, that's fine.
Sound familiar?
- If you cut out the animal protein
and the animal fat,
which has in the literature clearly proven
to cause gut disease, if you
cut this junk outta your diet,
you are gonna be healthier.
- Why do I say it's a little bit better?
Well, if I look at historical data,
it tells us that animal
protein versus plant protein,
plant protein wins.
So if this is a plant
protein, it's going to win.
- One of the quotes that I
really love is from Wendell Berry
who said, "The problem that
we have is that, you know,
we've got a food care system
that doesn't care about health
and a healthcare system that
doesn't care about food."
And that's how we get into
the problem that we're in.
(intense music)
- The food industry uses
those same tobacco industry tactics,
twisting the signs,
misinformation, the same scientists
for hire paid to downplay
the risk of cigarette smoke
and toxic chemicals, are the same paid for
by the National Confectioners Association
to downplay the risk of candy.
And the same paid for by the meat industry
to downplay the risks of meat.
Whereas processed foods and animal foods
we're talking 14 million
lives lost every year.
So those of us involved in
this evidence-based nutrition
revolution, we're talking
about 14 million lives
in the balance.
So plant-based eating can be considered
kind of the modern day
nutritional equivalent
of stopping smoking.
But how long do we have to
wait before the CDC says,
"Don't wait for open heart surgery
before starting to eat
healthier," as well.
Until society changes,
we need to take personal
responsibility for our own health,
for our family's health.
We can't wait until society
catches up to the science again
because it's a matter of life and death.
The science was there since the 1930s.
We've known that tobacco
associated with lung cancer,
yet it took literally decades
before the powers that be
have actually came out and said it.
We are in the same situation today.
We have this mount of
evidence implicating our diet
as the leading killer of men
and women in the United States,
yet we're still not seeing
pronouncements from on high,
just the acknowledgement
of the available science.
So that means we have
to take our own health,
the our own family's health,
we have to take a responsibility for it
until we finally get
that acknowledgement of the science.
It's gonna be a while before
we can see warning labels
before ads on TV saying don't wait
until the cancer diagnosis
before you stop smoking.
The same thing with diet.
And so we're just in that window.
We're in that transition period
where the science is there
for anyone to see,
but it's just kind of
hidden upon public view.
And so we just need to get it out there.
- And because these underlying
biological mechanisms
are so dynamic, you know,
and so for someone who, you know,
gets 30 or 40 episodes
of chest pain a day,
can't walk across the street
without getting chest pain
or make love with their spouse
or play with their kids,
or go back to work without
having angen or chest pain,
and usually within a few weeks
they're essentially pain free.
- That's been my whole life,
is to get the word out.
The good news that we
have tremendous power
over our health destiny and longevity.
The vast majority of
premature death and disability
is preventable with a plant-based diet
and other healthy lifestyle behaviors.
- Michael, you know, he was
always very independent.
You know, he never talked about it,
but he just decided he was
not going to eat meat anymore.
He's a good kid.
He spent two years, he
just went from one place
to another giving lectures.
He didn't have a place to live.
He'd stay in somebody's
couch or something.
He got to know a lot of people.
(audience clapping)
- So when Dr. Dean Ornish published
his landmark lifestyle heart trial,
proving with something called
quantitative angiography
that indeed heart disease
could be reversed,
arteries opened up without
drugs, without surgery,
just a plant-based diet
and other healthy lifestyle behaviors,
I assumed this was gonna
be the game changer.
1990 when Dr. Dean Ornish's
lifestyle heart trial came out,
that was the turning
point personally for me
and should have been the turning
point for all of medicine.
I mean, my family had seen
it with their own eyes,
but here it was in black and white
published some of the most
prestigious medical journals
in the world, yet nothing happened.
Remember, there's this
hidden mountain of evidence.
It's not hidden in the literature,
the medical literature,
it's there for anyone to
go to a medical library
and down into the dusty
stacks of the basement
to pull it out.
It's like those 6,000 tobacco
studies, right? Just here.
Look, if you would still wanna smoke,
it's your body, your choice.
Smoke, go bungee jump,
disconnect all the smoke
alarms in your house,
whatever you want to do,
whatever floats your boat.
But just know the predictable
consequences of your actions.
I said wait a second,
if effectively the cure
to our number one killer could get lost
down some rabbit hole and ignored,
what else might there be
in the medical literature
that could help my patients
but just didn't have a corporate budget
driving its promotion?
Well, I made it my life's
mission to find out.
For those of you unfamiliar
with my work, every year I read
through every issue of
every English language
nutrition journal in the world
so busy folks like you don't have to.
(audience laughing)
And then compile all the most interesting,
most groundbreaking,
most practical findings
to new videos and articles
that I upload every day
to my non-profit site, nutritionfacts.org.
(audience cheering)
Everything on the website is free.
There's no ads, no corporate sponsorship,
strictly non-commercial, not
selling anything, no kickbacks.
We just put it up as a
tribute to my grandmother.
(intense music)
- If everyone ate the way I ate
or the way I tell patients to eat,
I'd somewhat be out of business.
If people ate like that, yeah,
it would be a humongous
change in healthcare.
It would be very preventative
to a vast majority
of the diseases that we have
because that diet is
taking out meat and dairy,
which we know from epidemiology,
we know from randomized controlled trials,
we know from looking at societies
that live long healthy
lives like the blue zones,
that stuff is bad for you.
And so really what's left
is this just life affirming,
life giving fruits,
vegetables, antioxidants,
phytonutrients fiber that
fosters a perfect microbiome.
Yeah, that would just eliminate disease
or vastly reduce it.
The actual doctors
from the Dietary Guidelines
Advisory Committee,
they say eat less meat.
They say eat more fruits and vegetables.
If you look at the plate that
the government recommends,
it's a quarter fruit,
a quarter vegetables,
a quarter grains, and then
it's say a quarter protein.
But if you then go and look
at where our tax dollars are spent,
are they spent a quarter on fruits,
a quarter on vegetables?
No, not at all.
It's spent mainly on meat
and dairy and grains,
but most of that grains to
go to feed meat and dairy.
So I think it's important
for the government
to do something, but you could
see where there's a problem
with the government doing anything
as long as we allow
lobbyists to drive policy,
which we do in our current system.
- So where did Pritikin
get his evidence from?
Well, you know, a network of
missionary hospitals set up
throughout Sub-Saharan
Africa uncovered what may be
one of the most important
advances in health.
The fact that many of our major diseases
were universally rare, like heart disease.
The African population
of Uganda, for example,
coronary artery disease,
was almost non-existent.
You say, wait a second, our
number one cause of death,
almost non-existent.
What were they eating?
Well, they we're eating lots
of vegetables and grains
and greens and their
protein almost entirely
from plant sources.
And they had the cholesterol
levels to prove it.
Very similar to what we see
in modern day plant eaters.
(intense music)
So wait a second,
maybe they were just dying
early from something else.
Never lived long enough
to get heart disease. No.
Here's age match heart
attack rates in Uganda
versus St. Louis.
Now 632 autopsies in Uganda,
only one myocardial infarction.
Outta 632 age and gender match autopsies
in Missouri, 136 myocardial infarctions.
More than a hundred times the rate
of our leading killer.
In fact, they were so
blown away, went back,
did another 800 autopsies.
Ugandan still just that
one small healed infarct,
meaning it wasn't even the cause of death.
Out of 1,427 patients, less
than one in a thousand.
Whereas here, heart
disease is an epidemic.
(intense music)
(audience clapping)
- He got arrested a couple of times.
In fact, in his medical school book,
everybody has a page of the graduates
and everybody has a picture
of them and their wives
or children and that
Michael had his mugshot.
(intense music)
This was when he was in medical school
and he got arrested several times.
- Following the footsteps of my parents
who were arrested over and over
during the civil rights movement,
in between classes at med school,
I would go feed people on the commons
with the organization Food Not Bombs,
which was technically illegal
and helped move homeless families
into empty city-owned housing
units with Homes Not Jails.
All my arrests were for civil disobedience
upholding Article 25 of the
UN Declaration of Human Rights
that everyone has a right
to a standard of living,
adequate for the health
and wellbeing of themselves
and their family,
including food, clothing,
housing, and medical care.
(intense music)
(audience clapping)
With enough portion control,
anyone can lose weight.
Lock someone in a closet,
you can force them to lose
as much body fat as you want.
Chaining them to what treadmill
would've a similar effect.
But what's the most
effective weight loss regime
that doesn't involve caloric restriction
or exercise or a felony?
Well, I have scoured
through the medical literature
and all the randomized controlled trials.
And the single most
successful strategy to date
is a diet of whole plant foods.
The single most effective
weight loss intervention
like that ever published
in the peer reviewed
scientific literature,
a whole food plant-based diet.
(intense music)
The most frustrating thing
about being a physician
in primary care
is our patients don't get better.
About 80% of what a
primary care physician sees
in their practice are things
like type two diabetes,
obesity, high blood pressure,
things that just get worse,
worse, worse then you die.
And so what physicians can
do is prescribe medications
to try to slow down the rate
at which their diabetics
go blind, at which their
diabetics go on dialysis
or lose their lower limbs.
Because they're not treating
the underlying cause,
all they're doing is kind
of trying to slow the rate
of the demise of their patient.
That's why lifestyle
medicine is so important.
If we can treat the underlying
cause, we can prevent arrest
and even reverse some
of the chronic diseases
that are decimating our population.
(intense music)
- Every one of us physicians
who practices a lifestyle medicine
and gets our patients on
whole food, plant-based diets,
we witness this remarkable transformation,
this kind of food stream
flowing through the body,
meal after meal, week after week,
produces wonderful
effects that within days
the obesity starts to melt
away and the arteries open up
and the high blood pressure comes down
and the joints stop hurting.
And the asthmatic lungs
stop wheezing so much,
the migraine headaches get better
and people turn into
normal healthy people,
normal heights and normal
weights and blood pressures
and they don't need a lot of pills
and potions and procedures.
- We're all the same when
it comes to eating food.
We can maintain ethnic cuisines
of course using the flavors
and spices and herbs and stuff like that.
But we should be eating quite frankly,
whole plant-based foods.
We're looking at a solution
for creating health
unlike anything we've ever seen before.
- Surely if there was some safe,
simple side effect-free solution
to the obesity epidemic,
we would know about it by now, right?
I'm not so sure.
It may take an average of 17 years
before research evidence makes it
in day-to-day clinical practice.
To take one example
that was particularly
poignant for me and my family,
heart disease.
Decades ago Dr. Dean
Ornish published evidence
in one of the most prestigious
medical journals in the world
that our leading cause of
death could be reversed
with diet and lifestyle changes alone.
Yet hardly anything changed.
Even now, hundreds of
thousands of Americans
continue to needlessly die every year
from what we learned decades ago
was a potentially reversible condition.
I had seen it with my own eyes.
(intense music)
- These are choices that people make.
I always used to say that, you know,
the coronary heart disease
is culinary heart disease
mispronouncing it on purpose, okay?
And saying that it's an elbow problem.
(intense music)
When the patient's in
the coronary care unit,
I'm usually seeing them
'cause I'm not doing invasive cardiology,
I'm seeing them on
rounds the next morning.
Okay, so I say "I'm gonna
ask you to do a little quiz
with me just to tell me
where you are in terms of your thinking.
And I'm gonna ask you some questions
and they sound a little silly,
but you have just humor me
and let's see how far
we can get with this.
Tell me what happened to
you while you're here."
And I say, "I had a heart attack."
"That's right, how did
the heart attack happen?"
"Well, they told me I
had a blocked artery."
"That's right. What was it
blocked with?" "Plaque."
"That's right. What's plaque made out of?"
"Fat and cholesterol."
"That's exactly right.
And where did that fat and
cholesterol come from?"
The patient says 100%
of the time, "I ate it"
(intense music)
- [Michael] Back in 1903,
Thomas Edison predicted that
the doctor of the future
will give no medicine
but will instruct his patient in the care
of the human frame in
diet and in the cause
and prevention of diseases.
Edison's prediction hasn't come true.
(intense music)
- [Announcer] Why don't
we give a big warm welcome
to Dr. Michael Greger.
(audience cheering)
- You know, some people are
overwhelmed by medical articles
and research and you know,
having a way for somebody to,
you know, disseminate
that information to you,
I think is paramount.
I'm a cancer survivor.
I became a vegetarian shortly
after going through my treatments.
It's been about 15 years now.
I was learning a lot from the things
that Dr. Greger was publishing.
There's a lot of mixed
messaging out there about
what you should be eating
and what you should be doing.
One of the things I do
appreciate about Nutrition Facts
is it does make a lot of
the harder information
easier to consume.
I think his videos are engaging.
His personality is amazing.
If you aren't laughing,
I don't know what to say.
- The notion that a
calorie from one source
is just as fattening as any
other is a trope broadcast
by the food industry as
a way to absolve itself
of culpability.
Coca-Cola itself even put an ad out there
emphasizing this "one
simple common-sense fact."
As the current and past chairs
of the Harvard's Nutrition
Department put it,
"This central argument from industry
is that the overconsumption of calories
from carrots would be no different
than the overconsumption
of calories from soda."
If a calorie's just a
calorie, why does it matter
what we put in our mouth?
(intense music)
(opera singing)
It is true that in a tightly
controlled laboratory setting,
240 calories of carrots
would have the same
effect on calorie balance
than the 240 calories in a bottle of Coke.
(opera music)
But this comparison falls flat on its face
out in the real world.
You could chug those liquid candy calories
in less than a minute.
But eating 240 calories of carrots
would take you more than
two and a half hours
of sustained, constant chewing.
(audience laughing)
(opera music)
Not only would your jaw get sore,
but 240 calories of
carrots is like five cups.
You might not even be
able to fit them all in.
In a lab, a calorie is a
calorie, but in life far from it.
- Unfortunately, if you go to
your doctor, the doctor says,
"Take these pills to
lower your blood pressure
or your cholesterol or your blood sugar."
And they say, "Doctor, how
long do I have to take these?"
The doctor, he says, "Forever."
And the reason is that the pill
doesn't make you feel better,
but the lifestyle changes do.
And there's no point in giving
up something that you enjoy
unless you get something back
that's better and quickly.
And because these underlying
biological mechanisms
are so dynamic, when you
make really healthy changes,
eat well, move more,
stress less, love more,
most people feel so
much better so quickly.
It reframes the reason
for making these changes
from fear of dying,
which is not sustainable,
to joy and pleasure and love
and feeling good, which are.
- What amazing potential
the body has to heal itself.
I, as a physician have a lot to do
educating my colleagues.
Before you order another $1,000 scan,
another $500 set of blood tests,
ask your patient what they ate yesterday.
And if it's full of
burgers and buffalo wings,
then that's where to start.
Send the patient to a plant-based
dietician down the hall.
Take them shopping and
stock their refrigerator up.
- Medical education practice
is funded by big pharma,
both in undergraduate and
postgraduate medical education.
I've never been offered to
been taken out to dinner
by big broccoli.
There's a reason for that.
These are the cash cow
drugs for big pharma.
Give a drug for a lifestyle condition,
that means you have to take
the drug every single day
for the rest of your life.
That's where the money is.
New blood pressure pill, new
cholesterol lowering pill.
And that's their bread and butter.
And here we come along
and say, "Wait a second.
No, no, we can lower your cholesterol
as much, if not better.
Have all these positive,
healthy side effects
with diet and lifestyle."
Yet it's just not as
profitable for big pharma.
- We really cannot
underestimate the public.
When you think back on it,
it took over 7,000 scientific papers
to finally get the Surgeon General to say
that smoking was harmful to your health.
Now since that has happened,
the amount of smokers have gone
from 40 million to 20 million.
(intense music)
- We really try to change
the outcome of our patients
by not just the modern
guideline-driven management
of medications and revascularizations
the latest therapies
that you can do with
this device for that one.
But really changing the,
what we like to say,
changing the paradigm by
turning off the faucet
instead of mopping up the floor.
(intense music)
(water bubbling)
- [Michael]
Drug companies are
more than happy to sell you
a new roll of paper towels every day
for the rest of your life
while the water continues to gush.
- A hundred years in a row
that cardiovascular disease
is the leading killer of Americans.
It's time that we actually
start really turning
off the faucet instead of
just mopping up the floor.
- Is it really true
that protein might increase cancer risk?
And so being a biochemist as I am,
we had an opportunity also
of not only determining
whether that's true, but if
it is true, how does it work?
So we spent many of those
years at first showing
that yes, it is true.
When I say yes, it is true,
I mean, when animals are fed
higher levels of protein,
animal protein, they get cancer.
But at lower levels they don't.
And one of the key
experiments that we did,
I found very, very exciting
was that we could turn on
and turn off cancer
growth just by adjusting
the level of the protein, animal protein.
(intense music)
That was very exciting
for some various reasons.
One of which is the idea
now recognized these days
at least by me, that we can
control cancer by nutrition.
(intense music)
The second thing related
to that was the idea
that we could actually reverse cancer
'cause that's what we did.
- Let me share with you what's been called
the best kept secret in all of medicine.
The best kept secret in medicine
is that sometimes given
the right conditions,
the body can sometimes heal itself.
You know, if you, you know,
whack your shin really hard
in a coffee table, right?
Get a red hot, painful, swollen, inflamed,
but will heal naturally if you stand back,
let your body work it's magic.
Okay, what if you hit
yourself in the same place
day after day or three times
a day, breakfast, lunch
and dinner, you'd never heal.
You'd go to your doctor, you'd be like,
"Ah, my shin hurts."
They'd be like, "No problem."
Whip out their pad.
Write your prescription
for it, pain killers.
You're still whacking your
sin three times a day.
Still really hurts like heck,
but oh, feel so much better
with those pain pills on board.
Thank heavens for modern medicine.
(audience laughing)
Our body wants to come back
to health if we let it.
But if we keep reinjuring
ourselves, keep stabbing ourselves
with a fork three times
a day, we may never heal.
You know, one of the most
amazing things I learned
in all my medical training
was that within 15 years
of stopping smoking,
your lung cancer rates approach
that of a lifelong non-smoker.
Isn't that amazing?
Like your lungs can clear out all that tar
and eventually, it's almost
as if you never started smoking at all.
Where our body wants
to come back to health.
And so every morning of our smoking life,
that healing process starts until wham
first cigarette of the day.
Reinjuring our lungs with every puff,
just like we can reinjure our arteries
with every bite.
When all we had to do all along,
the miracle cure is just stand back,
get out of the way, stop
re-damaging ourselves
and let our body's
natural healing processes
bring us back towards health.
Sure you can choose moderation
and hit yourself with a smaller hammer,
(audience laughing)
but why beat yourself up at all?
We've known about this for decades.
"American Heart Journal,"
1977 cases like Mr. F.W here,
heart disease so bad,
couldn't even make it
to the mailbox.
Started eating healthier.
Few months later, he was
climbing mountains, no pain.
(audience laughing)
All right.
- We really do like to
improve people's outcomes.
And even though it may cost
us revenue in a given patient,
because most of our people
who follow their
medication do the exercise
and do plant-based
nutrition, don't come back
to the stress lab and they don't come back
to the coronary care unit.
And we're not making money
off of those people anymore.
But it opens us up for new patients.
And so, you know, the people
who really are not following
the program, they're smoking,
they're eating animal products,
high fat, high sodium,
they're coming back in
and out of heart failure
and hospital readmissions are a problem.
But the people who
actually adopt lifestyle,
we're moving their clinic visits out
from six or 10 weeks to six to 10 months
and seeing them sometimes once a year.
And that actually does
give us access to try
and help the community around us.
We are in an area that's saturated
with cardiovascular diseases,
a lot of Hispanic patients,
a lot of African American patients,
but really all varieties.
The burden of cardiovascular disease
is so great in around the country.
- You know, if we wanted to make money,
you go to the stock market or something,
people go into medicine
because they care about
people, yet we get in there
and our patients don't get better.
I've heard these stories so many times
from my lifestyle medicine
colleagues that, you know,
in the back of my mind I'm thinking,
I've been telling you this,
like there's a mountain
of peer reviewed medical evidence
going back decades proving this.
But no, it took the one anecdote,
like the one person in front
of you to change your mind.
Same with the risk of
cognitive impairment.
Only healthy plant-based
diets reduce risks.
Same with dementia and
depression. The same with frailty.
Healthy, plant foods, good,
plant-based junk, bad.
And the same with aging.
The more people cut down
on meat, dairy, and eggs,
the slower they appear to age.
But that's only if they replace them
with healthy plant foods.
Pile on the junk and you
can accelerate aging.
That's why Cornell professor
emeritus biochemistry,
T. Colin Campbell coined
the term whole food,
plant-based diet.
- Reversing cancer by nutritional means,
cancer being promoted
by animal-based protein,
the most revered of all
nutrients for a century or two.
- The more that
information gets out there,
the more patients are gonna show up
to their doctors getting healthier.
And that's not what people do.
People don't get healthier over time.
And so when that happens,
that really opens the eyes.
- And if we could just get
everybody to understand
what is good nutrition.
And that of course starts
not just with parenting,
it starts with cardiologists.
The leading cause of
death is of cardiologists,
it's still heart disease.
Plenty of people who get a
stent put in by a cardiologist
and they're now told
nothing about their diet.
And when I see that
I don't just worry about the patient,
I will worry about the provider.
Because if they don't know
to tell the patient that,
it's gonna get them.
- As my good friend Kim Williams who said
"There are two types of
cardiologists, those who are vegan
and those who have not yet
read the literature." (laughs)
- The sicker people are,
the more they spend money,
the more they can charge for premiums.
Again, these perverse incentives
where the less healthy people
are, the more money is made.
I mean it's just an
unfortunate kind of consequence
of our for-profit medical system.
But again, we can step
back, stick with the signs
and save ourselves and our families.
(intense music)
1930s, a group of diabetics
placed on a plant-based diet
over a period of five years.
A quarter of them were able
to get off insulin altogether.
But plant-based diets
tend to be relatively low calorie diets.
I mean, maybe their diabetes got better
just because they lost so much weight.
To tease that out, what we'd have to do
is put people on a plant-based diet
but force them to eat so much food
that they don't lose any weight.
Then we can see if there's
some, you know, unique benefits
to plant-based eating beyond
just all the easy weight loss.
Well we'd have to wait
44 years, but here it is.
Insulin needs were cut
60% across the board,
half the diabetics ended off
all their insulin altogether.
Wow, how many years did that take?
No, 16 days.
16 days later.
So we're talking diabetics
who've had diabetes for 20 years,
injecting 20 units of insulin a day
and then 13 days later on, none.
Diabetes for 20 years,
then off all insulin
in less than two weeks.
Diabetes for 20 years
'cause no one had told them
about a plant-based diet.
For decades, they were
13 days away at any time
from being free.
Lower blood sugars on
32 units less insulin.
That's the power of plants.
And as a bonus, cholesterol
drop like a rock
to under 150 again in 16 days.
So just like making
moderate changes in diet
may only net you modest
reductions in cholesterol.
How moderate do you want your diabetes?
Asking diabetics to make
moderate changes in diet
can leave them with moderate blindness,
moderate kidney failure,
moderate amputate,
maybe just a few toes or something.
(audience laughing)
Moderation in all things isn't
necessarily a good thing.
You know, there's a famous
study published in a journal
called "Cell Metabolism,"
which purported to show
that diets high meat,
eggs and dairy could be as
harmful to health as smoking.
Explaining that for those in middle aged
who eat a lot of meat, eggs, and dairy,
four times as likely to
die from cancer, diabetes.
But if you look at the actual study,
you'll see that's simply not true.
Those eating a lot of
animal protein in middle age
didn't have four times the
risk of dying from diabetes
they 73 times the risk
of dying from diabetes.
Now those only eating a moderate
amount of animal protein,
oh, they just had 23
times the risk of death.
The academic institution
where this study was done
sent out a press release
with a memorable opening line,
"That chicken wing you're eating
could be as deadly as a cigarette."
Eating lots of a diet
rich and animal protein
four times as likely to die from cancer.
I mean that's comparable
to what one might get smoking, right?
So I mean, what was the response
in the academic community
to this revelation that diets high meat,
eggs and dairy could be
harmful to health of smoking?
Well, one nutrition scientist
said it was potentially
dangerous to tell people
about this study, why?
Well, smoker might think,
"Why bother quitting smoking?
My ham and cheese sandwich
is just as bad for me."
(audience laughing)
So let's not tell anyone about this
whole meat and cheese thing shhh.
Reminds me of a famous
Philip Morris cigarette ad
that tried to downplay the risk by saying,
"Hey, you think secondhand smoke is bad,
increasing the risk of lung cancer 19%.
Well hey, drinking one or two
glasses of milk every day,
three times as bad, 62%
increased risk of lung cancer."
Tripling your risk of heart disease
by eating non-vegetarian.
Multiplying your risk sixfold if you eat
lots of meat and dairy.
So they concluded,
let's keep some perspective here.
(audience laughing)
The risk from secondhand
smoke may be well below that
of other everyday activities.
So breathe deep.
(audience laughing)
That's like saying it, don't
worry about getting stabbed
because getting shot so much worse.
(audience laughing)
How about neither? Two
risks don't make a right.
Of course, we'll note Philip
Morris stopped throwing dairy
under the bus once they
purchased Kraft Foods.
Just saying.
(intense music)
For a while I was thinking,
I mean the insurers,
you would think the ones, the payers,
you'd think they'd be clamoring for this
because it would save them so much money.
But then you realize they
just get a part of the pie.
And the bigger the pie,
the more money they make,
the sicker people are,
the more they spend money,
the more they can charge for premiums.
Again, these perverse incentives.
- Obesity has become very common
because we are not only eating
a tremendous amounts of calories,
way in excess of what our bodies require,
but the particular combination of sugars
and fats eaten at the same time
evokes what's called oxidative priority.
We burn the sugars and
store the fats for later.
So when you eat something like ice cream,
it is fat and sugar.
You burn the sugar and store the fat.
When you eat a cheeseburger,
you're gonna burn the sugar
in the white flour bun and
then the sugar and the ketchup
and store the fat in
the meat and the cheese.
So we're eating that sugar fat combination
pretty much all day from
the bacon and eggs and toast
in the morning to the
burgers and fries at lunch
and to the fried chicken and
the milkshake in the evening.
Even the broiled salmon eaten
with the grilled potatoes
is that fat and sugar combination.
So the vast amounts of fat
and sugar that we're eating
on a daily basis is
making us grossly obese.
And it's more than just a cosmetic issue
because as fat accumulates,
especially inside the abdomen,
intrabdominal fat puts out
on an array of molecules
that sets off inflammation.
They're called inflammatory cytokines
and they set off inflammatory
conditions all over the body.
So obesity basically is
a state of inflammation.
People can say, "Well, I'm
obese, but I'm still healthy."
No, if you're obese, you're
fighting inflammation.
And that sets the stage for diseases
in many kinds of organs.
- Who says that, you know,
African Americans are
genetically predisposed, not so.
We have about a 21% higher
cardiovascular mortality rate
in the black community of this country,
and it really does have
to do with the diet.
It was called out by the
Regards Trial investigators.
Anyone can look that
up to the Regards Trial
and you'll see these publications
that say the Southern diet
and what they really mean
by that, the soul food.
It's taking your greens and
putting ham hocks in it,
or taking the yams and
making candy yams out of it.
So more cholesterol, more saturated fat,
not just chicken, but fried chicken.
And if you have that sodium content,
the cholesterol content,
saturated fat and sodium
with sugar, that's a
combination that is set up
for heart disease, kidney
disease, stroke, and death.
(intense music)
- Each year you are reborn.
You create and destroy nearly
your entire body weight
in new cells every year.
Your cells are pre-programmed
to die naturally,
to make way for fresh cells.
In a sense, your body's
rebuilding itself every few months
with the building materials
you provided through your diet.
Some cells, however,
overstay their welcome,
namely cancer cells.
By somehow disabling their
own suicide mechanisms,
they don't die when they're supposed to.
Because they continue
to thrive and divide,
cancer cells can eventually form tumors
and potentially spread
throughout the body.
All cells contain
so-called death receptors
that trigger the
self-destruction sequence.
But cancer cells can disable
their own death receptors.
Vegetables are selective.
They destroy cancer cells,
but leave normal cells alone
and underscores the
importance of including
a variety of vegetables in your diet.
(intense music)
- What is the science of the disease?
And by that I mean the following,
if we can have them understand
that all experts in
this disease would agree
that where cardiovascular disease
has its inception, its
onset, its beginning,
is when we progressively
injure the life jacket
and the guardian of our blood vessels,
which happens to be that
delicate innermost lining,
the endothelium.
And what truly makes the
endothelium so magical
is the molecule of gas, nitric
oxide, that it produces,
which is the great protector
and salvation of all of our blood vessels
because of its remarkable functions.
For example, nitric oxide
will keep all the cellular
elements within our
bloodstream flowing smoothly
like Teflon rather than Velcro.
Number two, nitric oxide is
the strongest blood vessel
dilator in the body.
When you climb stairs, the
arteries to your heart,
to your legs, they widen, they dilate.
That's nitric oxide.
Number three, nitric oxide
keeps the wall of the artery
from becoming thick and stiff or inflamed.
Protects us from getting high
blood pressure, hypertension.
Number four, and this is the absolute key.
Number four, a safe and
normal amount of nitric oxide
will protect us all
from ever developing blockages or plaque.
However, anybody who develops
cardiovascular disease,
whether they're in New York,
Chicago, London, Berlin,
is because in the previous decades,
they now have so sufficiently
trashed, injured, compromised,
and turned their endothelial
system into a train wreck.
They no no longer have enough nitric oxide
to protect themselves from
making blockages and plaque.
But the good news here is this,
this is not a malignancy.
And once you get patients
to stop ever again
passing any morsel through their lips,
it is going to further destroy
an already train wrecked endothelium.
Then rapidly the endothelial,
the system recovers,
makes enough nitric oxide.
So, you know, not only
can you halt the disease,
but often we'll see significant elements
of disease reversal.
- Any lifestyle medicine
doctor can tell you this,
is where all of a sudden
people get better.
In fact, it's interesting when I go
to these lifestyle medicine conferences
and talk to my fellow physicians
and I ask them the question, which is,
how did you get into this?
Like, you know, I mean,
none of us were taught this
in medical school.
So why are you here?
Like, what was the light bulb moment?
'Cause of course, I
wanna find out what it is
so I can tell the rest of my colleagues.
And you know, more often
than not, it's a patient.
It's a patient that educated them.
All of a sudden, one of the patients
that's been coming to them for years,
all of a sudden they look great.
They lost all this weight.
In fact, they probably came to them
because all of a sudden their
blood pressure's too low,
they're overmedicated
and said, "Wait a second.
I've been following you and
your family for all these years.
What happened?"
You know, and they're like,
"Oh, I read the China Study,
or I saw, you know, 'Forks over Knives,'"
or they got a hold of some resource
and then change their whole lives,
change the lives of their family
and their doctors just spell
bound thinking to themselves,
in the back of their mind.
"Wait a second, I've got
like thousands of patients
just like you."
- You know, half to two thirds of people
prescribed cholesterol or
drugs aren't taking them
after just four to six months,
even though they're proven value in people
who have heart disease.
But when paradoxically, you know,
Medicare has been covering
my lifestyle program
for reversing heart disease.
And most of the major insurance companies
are now doing that.
And we've been training
hospitals and clinics
and physician groups around the country,
and we're getting bigger
changes in lifestyle,
better clinical outcomes,
bigger cost savings,
and better adherence
than anyone's ever shown.
- This is nature. This
is a fact of nature.
What we're discovering, once
again, is how nature works.
And that's what goes on
inside of a cell, one cell.
And we have some people actually
maybe between 10 and a hundred
trillion cells in a body,
and each of them doing their own thing.
This is all operating in a symphonic way.
Once you get to this point of realization,
you get this kind of empirical data.
You cannot argue, "Oh, it's
the other way around." No.
- Alright, high blood pressure,
78 million Americans affected.
That's one in three American adults.
As we get older, pressures
get higher and higher.
(indistinct) age 60, most of
us have high blood pressure.
So wait a second.
If most of us get hypertension, well,
maybe it's just a natural
inevitable consequence of aging.
No, we've noticed since the 1920s,
high blood pressure need not occur.
Researchers measured the blood pressures
of a thousand people
living in rural Kenya.
Typical Kenyan diets, something like this.
Corn, beans, vegetable, fruit, greens.
Our pressures go up as we
age, such that by age 60,
most of us have high blood pressure.
Their pressures go down
and the lower the better.
So 140 over 90 cutoff is arbitrary.
I mean, even people with
pressures under 120 over 80
may benefit from blood pressure reduction.
So the ideal blood pressure,
the no benefit from reducing
it further blood pressure
110 over 70.
Is it even possible to get
pressures down to 110 over 70?
It's not just possible.
It's normal for those
living healthy enough lives.
Two years of this rural Kenyan hospital,
1800 patients were admitted.
How many cases of high blood
pressure did they find? Zero.
Wow. Must have had low rates
of heart disease, right?
No, they had no rates of heart disease.
Now, the single case of arteriosclerosis,
our number one killer was found.
Rural China, same thing.
About 110 over 70 their entire lives.
70 year olds with same blood
pressure as 16 year olds.
It's amazing in Asia, Africa,
vastly different diets.
What they shared in common
is that they're plant-based
day to day with meat only
eaten on special occasions.
It's amazing, why do we think
is the plant-based nature
of their diets that was so protective?
Because in the western world,
according to American Heart Association,
the only group of folks
getting it down to that low
on average, are those eating
strictly plant-based diets,
coming in at a perfect 110 over 65.
This is the largest group of largest study
of plant-based eaters in history
following 89,000 Californians,
comparing non-vegetarians
to so-called semi vegetarians,
those who eat meat more on a
weekly basis than a daily basis
compared to those who
eat no meat except fish,
compared to those who eat no meat at all,
compared to those who eat
no meat, eggs, or dairy.
And this was an Adventist study,
so even the non-vegetarians
didn't eat a lot of meat
compared to the general population.
Ate lots of fruits and vegetables,
tend not to smoke, and exercise.
This is a really healthy
group of meat eaters.
But still we see this
kind of stepwise drop
in high blood pressure rates
the more and more plant-based people ate.
Same thing with diabetes,
same thing with obesity.
You can show this experimentally.
You take vegetarians, you give them meat,
pay them enough to eat it, and
their blood pressures go up.
Or you take people who already eat meat,
remove meat from their diet
and their blood pressures
go down within seven days.
And this is after the vast majority
had to stop their medications
or reduce their medications.
They had to stop the medications.
I mean, if you treat the
cause, eliminate the disease,
you can't be on multiple
blood pressure medications
with normal blood pressure.
You drop your pressures too
low, get dizzy, fall over,
hurt yourself.
Lower pressures your doctor
has to pull you off the pills.
Lower pressures on fewer drugs.
That's the power of plants.
(intense music)
- We've had about a 70% decrease
in cardiovascular mortality
just the time that I've been, you know,
from the time I went to
medical school until now.
And it was really a lot of thoughtful,
hardworking, dedicated physicians.
Andreas Gruentzig, coming
up with angioplasty,
which then became stenting.
We had people developing bypass
surgery, heart transplants,
you know, putting in defibrillators,
coming up with statins,
ALLHAT, the hypertension program
that really changed the paradigm
for how we treat blood pressure.
All of these things, all
these dedicated physicians,
all of this career that they dedicated
lose to a double cheeseburger, really?
That's really what's going on
and our CDC, Center for Disease Control,
is talking about it incessantly.
That our Medicare system
is gonna go broke,
if we don't change something,
and that mortality that we fought so hard
to get down is headed right back up.
So what are we gonna do about it?
I'm telling everybody
it's their patriotic duty
to do a whole food plant-based diet
and tell everybody about it.
(intense music)
- You know, a few years ago,
Dr. Kim Williams became president
of the American College of Cardiology.
He was asked in an
interview why he himself
follows the same diet he
recommends to all his patients,
strictly plant-based diet.
"I don't mind dying,"
Dr. Williams replied,
"I just don't want it to be my own fault."
(audience laughing)
Thank you so much, everyone.